Guide to the Alphonse Daudet Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alphonse Daudet Collection
1860-1899
GEN MSS 231
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(2 boxes)
Letters from Daudet to Henry Ceard (mentions Emile Zola and Alfred de Vigny), Estes and Lauriat, and Paul Ginisty of Odeon Theater, among others. Also includes a bound manuscript volume, partly in Daudet's handwriting and signed by him, entitled "Histoire de mes livres I. Fromont jeune et risler aîné."
Daudet, Alphonse, 1840-1897
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials acquired from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to Alphonse Daudet. Material acquired before 1998 has been organized into two series: Series I, Letters from Alphonse Daudet, and Series II, Writings. Material acquired after that date is located in Series III, Additions Since January 1998, which is arranged in accession order.
Alphonse Daudet, 1840-1897
Alphonse Daudet was a 19th century French novelist.
Authors, French -- 19th century; French literature -- 19th century; Authors -- France -- 19th century; Histoire de mes livres; Céard, Henry, 1851-1924; Daudet, Alphonse, 1840-1897; Vigny, Alfred de, 1797-1863; Zola, Émile, 1840-1902; Estes & Lauriat
- Letters from Alphonse Daudet, Series I
  - 7 ALS to Henry Céard, Paris, 1881-1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Emile Zola and Alfred de Vigny are mentioned in this group of letters.
  - ALS to André Ebner, his secretary, [n.p.], [1896?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ALS to [Estes and Lauriat?], Paris, 1877 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Acknowledging their purchase of the American translation and publication rights of Le Nabab.
  - ALS to Paul Ginisty, [n.p.], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ALS to Mme. Edouard Lockroy, [Paris?], 1891 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Accompanied by an engraved visiting card of Alphonse Daudet, bearing a few words in his handwriting signed with initials.
  - ALS to "Mon Directeur", [n.p.], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Accompanied by an English translation in another hand.
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, [Paris], [1864?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, [n.p.], 1872 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Writings, Series II
  - Histoire de Mes Livres. I. Fromont Jeune et Risler Ainé, [n.p.], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    MS, signed with pages 5-13 in Daudet's autograph, other pages with his corrections.
- Additions Since January 1998, Series III
  - [Swinn, B.?]
    - Portrait of Alphonse Daudet, 1888 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
      1 drawing: pencil; 22.3 x 11.6 cm. Head and shoulders portrait, turned 3/4 to the left. Manuscript caption, signed at upper right.
      Acc #: unknown
  - Daudet, Alphonse
    - ALS to Mr. Vanderem, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      1 item (1 L.); 15 cm x 9 cm. Asking him to forward a short story by a young author to a publisher.
      Acc #: 990118-d
    - ALS to Larroumet, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      1 item (1 L.); 15 cm. x 9 cm. Wishes to speak with him about his article.
      Acc #: 991018-d
    - ALS to M. Laisant, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      1 item (1 L.); 17 cm. x 11 cm. Recommends Dr. Vincent as the possible author of a "chronique d'hygiene." Accompanied by two letters to unidentified correspondents, one concerning the publication rights to Le Nabab, and one scheduling an appointment.
      Acc #: 20010424-d
    - L'evangeliste: manuscript notebook, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      1 item (ca, 100 L.); 17 cm. x 11 cm. Holograph notebook, much corrected, containing drafts and additions for L'evangeliste. Binding: contemporary blue boards. In case.
      Acc #: 20020729-l
    - ALS to Emile Pouvillon; Paris, 1878 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      1 item (1 L.); 15 cm. x 9 cm. Arranging to meet for dinner.
      Acc #: 20030206-z
    - Eighteen autograph letters, signed to Constant Coquelin; with Daudet's printed calling card, circa 1872 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Purchased from Pierre Berès (Hotel Drouot sale, 2003 November 18, lot 166), on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2004
    - Two autograph manuscript notebooks labelled "Critiques dramatiques", circa 1879-1880 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
      Purchased from Autographes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001
    - Bound volume containing an undated autograph letter, signed to "Cher Monsieur et ami" and an autograph manuscript poem, signed titled "La double conversion", circa 1860 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Purchased from the Moirandat Company AG (J. A. Stargardt sale, 2001 November 13-14, lot 55) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001
    - Two autograph letters, signed to [Edouard Thierry], [1875?] (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Purchased from Pierre Berès (Drouot Richelieu sale, 2001 November 27, lot 334), on the Edward J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002
    - Two autograph letters, signed to Georges [Charpentier]; with two undated autograph letters and a printed calling card for M and Mme Alphonse Daudet containing an undated autograph note regarding a dinner invitation, signed by Daudet's wife, Julia Daudet to unidentified recipients, 1878, 1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Purchased from Autographes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2004